<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice given unto the states of of [sic] the Lovv-Countries obedient &amp; faithfull to his Maiesty of Spaine, upon occasion of the letters written by Count Henry Vanden Bergh the 18. day of Iune 1632. to her Highnesse the Archdutchesse, and the estates in those dominions. As also unto the declaration made by him concerning his discontent received, being all fully answered and found to be unjust and unreasonable. If the reader please to compare them together, you shall find Henry of the Bergh his letters and declaration, printed in our aviso of Iune, the 30. Numb. 31. and Iuly 6. Numb. 32. Translated out of the French coppy.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103527</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839279</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14964)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 716:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice given unto the states of of [sic] the Lovv-Countries obedient &amp; faithfull to his Maiesty of Spaine, upon occasion of the letters written by Count Henry Vanden Bergh the 18. day of Iune 1632. to her Highnesse the Archdutchesse, and the estates in those dominions. As also unto the declaration made by him concerning his discontent received, being all fully answered and found to be unjust and unreasonable. If the reader please to compare them together, you shall find Henry of the Bergh his letters and declaration, printed in our aviso of Iune, the 30. Numb. 31. and Iuly 6. Numb. 32. Translated out of the French coppy.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 [i.e. 19], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. A[lsop] and T. F[awcet] for Nathaniel Butter, and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title page: August. 3. Numb. 38.</note>
                  <note>Printer's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Page numbers 9-19 misnumbered 7-17.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 18464.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18464 on UMI microfilm reel 716.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176890:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſt.</hi> 3. <hi>Numb.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p>ADVICE GIVEN VNTO THE STATES OF of the Low-Countries, obedient &amp; faithfull to his Maieſty of <hi>Spaine,</hi> upon occaſion of the Letters written by Count <hi>Henry Vanden Bergh</hi> the 18. day of <hi>Iune</hi> 1632. to her Highneſſe the <hi>Archdutcheſſe,</hi> and the <hi>Eſtates</hi> in thoſe Dominions.</p>
            <p>As alſo unto the declaration made by him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his diſcontent received, being all fully anſwered and found to be unjuſt and unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>If the Reader pleaſe to compare them together, you ſhall find <hi>Henry</hi> of the <hi>Bergh</hi> his Letters and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, Printed in our <hi>Aviſo</hi> of <hi>Iune,</hi> the 30. <hi>Numb.</hi> 31. and <hi>Iuly</hi> 6. <hi>Numb.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the French Coppy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>B. A.</hi> and <hi>T. F.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne.</hi> 1632.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176890:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:176890:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing that makes men more commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before the face of Heauen and Earth, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of true fidelity towards God and their Prince. It is a Primitive vertue which is borne with vs, and ought not to die but with vs without prejudice or wrong to any forraine Nations, it may bee averr'd with preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of honour, that there is not any place or Nation, where the Divine worſhip is more religiouſly obſerved, the Churches better maintayned and ſerved, the Cleargy more exemplary, the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity more pious, the people more devout and obſervant in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious duties, than in thoſe Provinces of the Low-countries which are ſubject and obedient to his Majeſty.
<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured"
                       resp="#MURP"
                       extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> tru<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured"
                       resp="#MURP"
                       extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Their Temples are in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and in effect to be numbred, and eſteemed amongſt the faireſt, and moſt adorned and beautified of all Chriſtendome, and the Doctrine of their Prelates in ſingular eſteeme with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> As concerning the fidelity due unto their Prince,
<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured"
                       resp="#MURP"
                       extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> do<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured"
                       resp="#MURP"
                       extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the ſame is immoveable and conſtant, &amp; hath beene ſo acknowledged and tryed by the continuance and proſecution of many ſucceeding yeares, yea ſuch, that maugre all the power, devices, and ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems of the enemie, and diſcontented braines, the ſame will ſtill ſubſiſt in integrity and true obedience.</p>
            <p>Wee are under a King the beſt that ever bore Crowne in many ages, the moſt pious, and beſt affectioned unto his ſul ſtitutes and ſuch as are in authority under him. At this day when Piety &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are ſo lively oppoſed &amp; ſet? upon in his Perſon and States by impiety and hereſie, when God and our Prince are both aſſaulted at once, whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e every man is now putting to his helping hand in the Ship untill the tempeſt be overpaſt, you will not (I aſſure my ſelfe) wonder if among a multitude and infinite number of good men, you ſhall find one wicked faithleſſe ſervant, who turnes his backe to his Maſter, and kiſſing him betrayes him, wonder not I ſay, if among ſo many faithfull ones you meet with one who under pretence of a Patriot and faithfull ſupporter of the Countryes, opens a way to eaſement.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:176890:3"/>
            <p>Our enemies are ſo much the more dangerous, by how much more they doe flatter vs. And as the promiſe of liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is nothing elſe but an Introduction of hereſie: So is the other of publike liberty tendered by the hand of a diſloyall one, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a deceitfull bayte to replunge our Provinces into the fore-paſſed calamities, out of which the mercy of the Omnipotent hath delivered and brought vs forth. Our ſweetneſſe (GOD bee bleſsed) is not mixed with any bitterneſſe, our Sacrifices are not intertu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bed or troubled, our lives paſſe along in tranquility, and under the manifold bleſſings of Heaven, under the example and government of a Princeſſe moſt devout and debonayre, and hope and expectation of a young Prince of Royall race. What is there now wanting to the height of our happineſſe, but the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Peace, which cannot be with-held from us, if wee make but ſome tryall and proofe worthy of our zeale and good will? We can doe much, if wee have but the will: onely let us have this care, that the want of courage turne not to our reproach &amp; ſhame, ſince that our domeſticke enemies are diſcryed &amp; brought to light, thoſe without ſhalbe inferiour to us. Our domeſticke enemies are ſuch, who under colour and pretence of rayſing up the publike liberty, labour and endeavour to deſtroy it by inovation, and bury the ſame in their owne ambitious engroſſing. And who having no other Religion but that of their ambition and of their owne inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, doe nevertheleſſe make profeſſion of being very good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes.</p>
            <p>The worſt cauſe that ever was in the world wanted not ſome pretence or other. There is nothing ſo like unto an Angell of light as a <hi>Daemon</hi> or Devill, nothing doth ſo counterfeyte, and appeare like unto the truth as falſhood &amp; a lye. You have (my Lords) ſeene the ridiculous pretences of Count <hi>Henry de Bergh</hi> in thoſe Letters which hee hath ſent to her highneſſe, to the States of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and the declaration which he made to ſollicite the fidelity of ſoldiers and men of honour. You have ſeene I ſay, his foundation without foundation, upon the which he grounds his perverſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. But the diſlike and diſtaſt which you have taken againſt his proceedings hath beene ſuch, and your loyalty and fidelity ſo commendable, that even to convince his felony, you have (with an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176890:3"/>extraordinary affection, &amp; love to the good of the Countrey) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed unto the Prince farre greater ayde and helpe than former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you had done. Moreover it is neceſſary that beſides you, the world be ſatisfied, which oftentimes doth judge by the outward appearance, not knowing the truth of things, and that the ſame may ſee the truth diſcovered, leſt men be abuſed by the cunning ſlights and pretences where withall he hides the groſſeneſſe and baſeneſſe of his treaſon. He begins his letter written to her high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with inſupportable and boldneſſe without meaſure, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting moſt traytour-like bread in one hand, and a flinty ſtone in the other. He expoſeth his wicked deſignes with all ſubmiſſion. Never I am ſure, was there any rebellion declared with more ſhameleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and impudency. After this his fayned Ceremony and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, he <hi>complaineth, that the Souldiers were withdrawne from his government, to the end that they might make him be the cauſe of their deſtruction.</hi> It is lawfull for a man to make his complaint but not perfidious. That which he ſayes is not truth, and the Letters of the Marquiſe <hi>De Sancte Croes</hi> doe teſtifie as much for he required no men from him, <hi>but onely beacuſe he judged that the enemy would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt nothing on that ſide, leaving all to his owne choiſe and deſiring him to ſee the Bridge well guarded and provided before</hi> Venlo, <hi>to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the troupes to paſſe over ſafely which ſhould be ſeat to relieve the ſame.</hi> And put the caſe, that which he affirmeth were true, if hee had beene well minded, and his intention good, he ought to have defended her government to the laſt man, and have kept himſelfe in the City of <hi>Gelder</hi> which is a ſtrong place, (as he had promiſed by Letters to her highneſſe, and allowing that <hi>Venlo</hi> was able to be held) &amp; therein have imitated the generoſity of his Brother Count <hi>Frederick,</hi> who in the yeare 1597. defended himſelfe within the City <hi>Lingen,</hi> even to the extreamity, with onely three Companies of foote and one of Horſe. But this, two dayes before the enemie did come before <hi>Venlo,</hi> called the Magiſtrates and told them, that the city would ſoon be beſieged, &amp; to take away the courage from the Citizens demonſtrated unto them the ſmall appearance and hope he had of defending the ſame. Wherefore hee excuſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from protecting of them, nay and beſides this being Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of that Province, ſaid he had other places to guard &amp; looke to,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176890:4"/>nevertheleſſe he preſently made haſt unto the City <hi>Gelder,</hi> from whence he departed preſently accompanied onely with one ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, or Companion, &amp; betooke himſelfe to <hi>Liege,</hi> there to put in execution the perfidiouſneſſe which he had plodded a long time.</p>
            <p>As <hi>for his ſervice of forty yeares,</hi> which he mentions: Tis true, in the beginning they were conſiderable, and of ſome worth when his brother (whoſe death he doth alleadge) did animate him by their good and valerous examples. But ever ſince, from the yeare 1606 that he defended the City <hi>Groll</hi> with expectation of reliefe by the Marquiſe <hi>Spinola</hi> who came time enough to reſcue him, his ſervices have not beene ſo remarkeable nor of ſuch moment, and moreover they have beene recompenced an hundred fold with dignities and titles, gifts, and honourable charges, and exceſſive ſummes of Money.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>the ill government of the Countryes,</hi> and the progreſse of our enemies, that proceeds from nothing elſe but from the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold treacheries, and the to too much confidence and truſt which our Princes have in his perſon, having with a fatherly and favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble affection which they bare unto their ſervants, indured a long time his diſcontentments, and greevances, which in time by little and little, and more and more are ſtill degenerated unto this action the moſt baſe and ignoble that ever could bee returned with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach unto a reaſonable Soule, manifeſted in theſe two branches, ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atitude, and revolt.</p>
            <p>One of the firſt teſtimonies of his diſloyall and evill will which he cunningly concealed, was obſerved at <hi>Bergen on Zoom</hi> in the yeare 1622. for then and here having received command reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by her Highneſse, to conduct the Marquiſe <hi>Spinola</hi> with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence unto the Army which he than had on the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> hee made a thouſand excuſes to prolong the time, and ſtay him or keepe him backe untill the want of reliefe cauſed us to rayſe the ſiege. And it was told the Marquiſe than, (who was in travaile with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiency, during this delay) by the Lieutenant of the Artillery, <hi>Wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gart</hi> by name, that he would looſe his head, if Count <hi>Henry de Bergh</hi> (whom he had knowne by long experience) did arriue, before the occaſion ſhould be let ſlip.</p>
            <p>He thought to have played the ſame prancke two yeares after,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176890:4"/>in like manuer to divert the ſiege of <hi>Breda,</hi> making profer of an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe upon <hi>Ravenſteyn,</hi> afterward upon the <hi>Grave,</hi> and laſtly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Caſtle of <hi>Genepe.</hi> The cunning Letters which after his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile manner he wrote full of excuſes, have ſufficiently diſcovered what was his deſigne. They are printed at large, in the hiſtory of the ſiege of <hi>Breda,</hi> compoſed and ſet forth by Father <hi>Hermanus Hugo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The confidence which her Highneſſe had euer ſince in his fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for the releeuing of <hi>Groll.</hi> In the yeare 1627. was the cauſe why wee loſt that City. For being there was a difference riſen betweene two Maiſters of the Campe, for the vantguard, being of different Nations, hee inſtead that hee ſhould haue rid them out of the Field, and done as it befitted him for his Maieſties ſervice, hee counſels the one not to yeild to the other, by that meanes in the meane time, to prevent them both from defeating a Convoy which eaſed and refreſhed the Enemie, for want of which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy the Enemie muſt of neceſſity haue raiſed the ſiege. Hee was put to his excuſe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> quitted becauſe his authority was not great enough for the deciding the preeminence of Nations, But let vs ſee, if hee hath better be haued himſelfe when hee had receiued more authority. The City named <hi>Shortogenboſch,</hi> was beſieged by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1629. Wee than praiſed God, becauſe the Enemie was fallen before a City which was able to defend it ſelfe and hold out vntill releife ſhould come. Her Highneſſe at that time vſed ſo much diligence, that in few dayes wee had a moſt flouriſhing Army on Foote and able to make a ſtrong aſſault. There was onely queſtion made, who ſhould command the ſame, the Marquis <hi>Spinola</hi> than being abſent. In the end this was the reſolution that Count <hi>Henry de Bergh</hi> ſhould haue the honour, and to this end hee was ſent for by her Highneſſe. No ſooner was hee come to <hi>Bruxels,</hi> but hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to propound an hundred difficulties one after another, and frame excuſes, to the end that the Enemie might gaine the more time to fortifie themſelues. In theſe extremicies, and by reaſon of the confidence which wee had in him, and partly by reaſon of his experience nothing was denied him which hee demanded. Many dayes paſſed in theſe entermedlings, but in the end hee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176890:5"/>goes to Field, and was by the way (ſo great haſt he made) from the 3. of <hi>June</hi> to the 27. and than hee found that the beſieged had not yet loſt one Inch of ground of all their outworkes, although the quarters of the Enemie were in good reaſonable defence. The advice of the moſt part of the Colonels was to open Trench a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt trench, and weary out the enimie in ſuch ſort, that hee ſhould not bee able to diſquiet the beſieged, and ſo expect vntill the Autumne ſhould bee paſt, and than the waters would cauſe him to depart of his owne accord, or at the leaſtwiſe bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to forſake ſome quarter or other, by which meanes wee might haue a way opened to bring in Munition, and ſoldiers and neceſſaries, as much as ſhould be required for the deliuerance of the City. Count <hi>Henry</hi> cannot approue this enterpriſe, indeed hee made tryall of ſome others, in thoſe places which were moſt fortified, and contented himſelfe with this concluſion, that the Enemies trenches were not poſſible to bee entred. Hauing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore intended a diuerſion of his Army hee leaues the ſiege, and ſends to hazard the paſſage of the <hi>Yſſel,</hi> by <hi>Lucas Cayro,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing paſſed happily, hee followed him, and ioynes the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Army with theirs, which Army was come for our aid and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. And what doth hee than? hee begins to treat with the Burgomaiſters of Cities, onely to repleniſh his owne Coffers, and famiſh the faireſt and compleateſt Army which had beene ſeene in a long time, in ſtead of demanding vp thoſe places where there were neither ſoldiers nor munition, and which doubtleſſe would haue ſurrendred at the very ſight of a ſtock of a tree, or the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt and ſimpleſt ſtroake which could haue beene made at them.</p>
            <p>You ſhall obſerue, if you pleaſe, an excuſable perfidiouſneſſe. When <hi>Lucas Cayro</hi> had paſſed the <hi>Yſſell.</hi> Contrary to the opinion of Count <hi>Henry,</hi> and that the terrour of an explioct ſo newly put in practice, and not foreſeeene had aſtoniſhed all <hi>Holland.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hauing aſſembled the whole Councell, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto them what had ſo lately and vnexpectedly happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, put into deliberation whether the ſiege ſhould bee rayſed yea or no. The aduice and opinion of all the Councell, and each of them was, that the <hi>Veluwee</hi> being thus occupied and poſſeſſed vnexpectedly, the Cities of <hi>Arnheym, Amersfort, Doesburgh,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176890:5"/>Wageningen, Rhenen,</hi> and other neare adioyning places about the <hi>Veluwee</hi> would bee taken without any reſiſtance at all, and that the gaine and profit which they ſhould make of <hi>Shertogenboſch</hi> could not countervaile nor recompence the leaſt of all thoſe loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which they ſhould ſuffer elſewhere, if their enimie were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ceaze vpon the very heart of the Country. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> did very much commend the advice of theſe Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, and ſaid, that verily ſome courſe muſt bee taken, if that which they obiected muſt needs fall out ſo, but hee could aſſure them to the contrary, and that the event would proue otherwiſe. And from whom I pray, could he haue this knowledge and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance but from Count <hi>Henry De Bergh,</hi> who in effect neuer made ſo much as any ſhew of demanding vp any City. Who within his owne view permitted the City <hi>Desburgh</hi> to be revictualled, and that was the cauſe that ſome poore <hi>Hollanders</hi> were executed being Catholicks, becauſe they had declared and manifeſted the intelligence which hee had receiued from them priuately. In a word <hi>Shertogenb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> was not releiued, and in effect nothing could be expected on his part ſince he had engaged himſelfe by promiſe to his ſiſters not to reſeue the ſame.</p>
            <p>What water can waſh him cleare from the loſſe of <hi>Weſel,</hi> which was taken from vs at the ſame time? ſeeing that as ſoone as euer he heard of the newes, hee kept himſelfe ſhut vp in his Chamber for 24. houres together, for feare leaſt hee ſhould bee required to ſend help to recouer the ſame City; and when as Count <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> hauing intreated him to furniſh him with men, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine that place, before the open breach where the Enemie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, was made vp, hee refuſed it. The Gouernour of <hi>Diden</hi> hath ſpoken it to Count <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> with his owne mouth that if hee had come to releiue the City of <hi>Weſell</hi> any time within fiue dayes after the ſame was taken hee might haue entred without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difficulty. If Count <hi>Henry</hi> had beene an honeſt man, wee had finiſhed our warre that yeare, and the Catholicke Religion, (with which cloake hee hides his baſeneſſe, and the blackneſſe of his Hypocriſie) had neuer ſuffered ſo much as the ſame hath done e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince.</p>
            <p>What wonders hath hee wrought? where are the great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploicts
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176890:6"/>of his Conqueſts? Let this alſo moreouer bee ſpoken for <hi>the great ſeruices</hi> which hee alleageth in Generall. Hee himſelfe hath oftentimes avouched, that he neuer hath receiued wound or hurt in the Kings ſeruice (notwithſtanding that ſome Hiſtories and report would haue made him beleeue that hee was once hurt in the leg or thigh, in a skirmiſh neere vnto <hi>Ruremond</hi> in the yeare 1598.) which hee attributed to a Mandegloire, or little figure or ſhape of a man, which hee ordinarily carried in a ſmall box, very durty and foule, which he hath ſhewed to more than one perſon.</p>
            <p>Indeed his ſeruices are well knowne, if euer any mans were; hee entred very poore into the ſervice of our Princes, and now at this inſtant hee is ſo rich that he poſſeſſeth millions. From a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Horſeman, and meaneſt of his houſe, hee was advanced to the greateſt offices which any ſervant of his Maieſty could aſpire vnto. And therefore hee hath great reaſon to ſay, <hi>that the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is not in that eſteeme as they ought to bee;</hi> ſeeing that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Offices, and Dignities are ſo ill beſtowed; and that hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone doth poſſeſſe that, which a dozen others better deſeruing than himſelfe would eſteeme themſelues happy to enioy. God bee thanked there are none that are vnprovided, and not one who hath juſt cauſe to complaine.</p>
            <p>Are they not farre engaged and employed in the houſe, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of their Soueraigne? Doe not they hold the moſt part of the Gouernments? Who doe poſſeſſe the principall Offices, and Eccleſiaſticall Dignities but thoſe of the Low-Countryes? If the <hi>Spaniſh, whom Count Henry vpbraides to bee the ſole Gouernours</hi> haue any part in the Government, and charge, it is for to expoſe their liues for our preſeruation, and proceeds from the great care which the King hath for our protection. Which this new refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mator qualifies with the name of <hi>Domination,</hi> intending thereby to make the ſame odious.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of the Country in particular, and thoſe of other nations, who vnanimouſly liue in ſervice here, and brotherly one with another, haue their part in the cheifeſt charges and offices as well as the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> The Marquis <hi>Spinola</hi> hath bad the Generalſhip both by Sea and Land; and at this preſent the Generalſhip both
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176890:6"/>of the Cavallery and Artillerye, are not poſſeſſed by the <hi>Spaniſh.</hi> Wee haue ſeene thoſe of theſe Countryes reciprocally in the Councels of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the managing of the moſt important matters: And wee haue ſuch ſtill at this preſent. Our diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Count <hi>Henry</hi> contradicts himſelfe, hee doth not remember that in his letter full of ſedition which hee wrote vnto the Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of theſe Countryes, hee confeſſeth that hee was called vpon by the King, to bee imployed in great affaires.</p>
            <p>The Nobility than is not in ſo ſmall eſteeme as hee would make the world beleeue, and his complaints are altogether without ground and foundation full of contradictions, ſeeing that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath beene honoured with the command of being Generall of the Army, when the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and other Nations haue beene ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded therefrom. It is hee himſelfe that hath loſt ſome of the Nobility. The Prince of <hi>Chimay,</hi> and the Baron <hi>De Belvoire,</hi> who haue beene diſpleaſed at their very death, ſeeing the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed by his <hi>Monopolies,</hi> will one day acouſe and reproach him before the throne of God, of the loſſe of twentie thouſand good men, which hee cauſed to languiſh in Miſery, to the end hee might vſe the Kings Enemies gently, who did contribute great ſummes of money to ſatiſfie his <hi>Avarice.</hi> The Father <hi>Hermanus Hugo,</hi> did in the Army reproach him at the very point of death, and could not ſurvive the publick Calamity.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Frederick</hi> his Brother ſhall accuſe him in like manner &amp; lay as much to his charge, for being ſo ſlack and remiſse, and lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all occaſion of releeuing the moſt Catholick City of <hi>Sherto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genboſch,</hi> which that Generous Cavallier hath formerly deliuered (in the yeare 1604) from the ſiege of Graue <hi>Maurice,</hi> who had blocqued vp the ſame. Let therefore Count <hi>Henry</hi> blame his owne inſatiable couetouſneſse for diſorder, and attribute the ill gouerment to himſelfe, without the which wee might at this day reioyce in a moſt happy and honourable peace, aſsuredly euen ſuch a peace which good ſubjects ought to wiſh vnto their Prince for the reputation of his Crowne.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Commiſſion of Maſter of the Field Generall, which hee ſaith was conferred vpon him two yeares agoe, by her Highneſſe in the name of the Kings Maieſty, and which hee is now reſolued to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176890:7"/>and execute for the ſervice of the Countryes, the preſeruation of the Privilidges, and the vpholding of the</hi> H. <hi>Catholicke, Apoſtolicall and Roman Church.</hi> You may thereby ſee vnto what a degree, and height of impudency the audaciouſneſse of this Traitor is come? How doth hee pay and recompence our good and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Princeſse with ingratitude? How doth hee accuſe her of Conniuance ſaying, <hi>that hee knowes that ſhe wiſheth that the affaires went better?</hi> And as it were acknowledging the goods deedes, and ſupreme honours which hee hath receiued from her extreame goodneſſe and bounty, hee hath ſo much boldneſſe and audacity to take her for a prote trix of his miſchiefe, and ſo doth declare himſelfe openly to bee guilty, as now hee is proclaimed. <hi>To bee guilty of crimen laeſae Maieſtatis in the higheſt degree,</hi> and capitall Enemie of the publike reſt, and therefore conſequently fallen away, and deprived of all his Honours, offices, Dignities, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt which hee hitherto hath had in his Maieſties ſervice.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1484. the Count <hi>de Rom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt</hi> did by the like prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice bare Armes againſt the Arch-Duke <hi>Maximilian</hi> his Lord, &amp; attributing in like manner to himſelfe the title of Captaine Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the Prince <hi>Philip</hi> his ſonne, hee wrote in this ſort to the States generall aſſembled in the City of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> his anſwer gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him was this. That they did not acknowledge him for ſuch, but an Enemie of the Prince and of the ſtate.</p>
            <p>As for the Countryes, in the name of God let him leaue them in peace, for there is no need of forging any innouation, wee need no broiles nor Traitor to trouble our tranquility. The flock would bee in good caſe vnder the clawes of the Wolfe, if our Religion had no better Protector. Oh had but this blacke ſoule as much capacity, and ability as hee hath hatred and malice, wee ſhould ſoone ſee a ſtrange Religion, and ſuch Lawes, that <hi>Saturue</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter</hi> would not bee brought in but for them onely. I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue how a man that hath no Religion at all: who hath falſified his Faith, and who in the yeare 1621. when hee went before <hi>Iulliers,</hi> by Teſtament written by his owne hand, which hee left to his ſiſter <hi>Anne,</hi> did ordaine to bee bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed or enterred in a prophane place neerer vnto his ſiſters, will not onely cloake and cover himſelfe with a vaile of Religion, but alſo counterfeite
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176890:7"/>himſelfe to bee a protector of the Catholike, Apoſtolicall, and <hi>Romiſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You deceiue your ſelfe Monſieur Count <hi>Henry,</hi> you muſt not ſend your manifeſtations and declarations into your Government of <hi>Geldria,</hi> hereof your Conſcience is to well knowne there, the City of <hi>Stefenſwert,</hi> which you haue made neutrall to ſerue for a retreat vnto the Enemies of the King, and to the Hereticks, and where you haue brought the Miniſters to poiſon the people and inſtruct your Siſters <hi>Anne,</hi> and <hi>Charloite,</hi> theſe ſhall teſtifie of your carriages, and your ſecret behaviour. Doe not you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that ſometimes by chaunce and through forgetfullneſse you left a little haereticall prayer booke in high-dutch on a ſeate in the Ieſuitiſh Church at <hi>Ruremond.</hi> Which booke you called your <hi>Haureman?</hi> you haue written to Prieſts and other perſons well qualified, and of diuers Nations, that your ſiſters were chriſtianly deceaſed, and that their ſoules were very happy. In the meane while you know, that they gaue vp the ghoſt in the Armes of ſuch Miniſters which you had procured them. Wee know more of your newes than you doe thinke for.</p>
            <p>Hee ends his letter with <hi>the retreat which hee had made into the City of</hi> Liege <hi>for the advancement of his deſſeyns.</hi> Wherein his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltye ill compacted together is failing; for the Deputes of the Prince and States of <hi>Liege,</hi> not willing to prejudice any way to ſo good neighbourhood, haue diſclaimed his action by a decree. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>une</hi> the 23. the contents whereof are theſe. <hi>A declaration publiſhed to ſhew that his letters and his declaration haue bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e publiſhed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any knowledge of theirs or participation, and conſent, and that they intend in no wiſe to entermeddle with any affaires of the ſaid Count Henry.</hi> Nay, for their better Iuſtification, they haue obliged him by a writing of his owne hand the 25. day of <hi>June.</hi> That they would haue it manifeſted. That as hee had publiſhed the ſaid let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters without hauing given notice or asked permiſſion of his H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Liege,</hi> or the Deputes of his ſtates, and how that hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended not by thoſe publications to attempt any thing againſt their right, nor envolue their affaires into his actions.</p>
            <p>This retreat of his hath beene intended along time, not <hi>for the ſervice of the Countryes nor Religion;</hi> but plotted and combined
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176890:8"/>with our Enemies. And if it were not, ſo how could hee haue had time enough to treate with <hi>the King and Princes</hi> which in the end of his Letter to the States he affirmes, <hi>to bee inclined to contribute their forces for the execution of his deſignes?</hi> But there are other ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proofes: &amp; it is not of a day or two that his treaſon hath bin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eproched unto him, and hit in his teeth by the brother of the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of the baſtard daughter, wee ſhall ſpeake of that in his due place, it is ſufficient for this point to manifeſt what is moſt true, that before ever the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> came to field to march to <hi>Venlo,</hi> hee had beene to conferre with him in <hi>Holland,</hi> and did ſo within a mile from the City, in the Caſtle of <hi>Holtmullen,</hi> where al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo was the Earle of <hi>Culenbergh,</hi> his brother in Law, and that before that time he had cauſed five Barrels of Silver to bee convayed to <hi>Meſeycke,</hi> there to buy the neceſsary proviſion for the ſiege of <hi>Maſtricht,</hi> under a colour that they were the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> his moneys deſtined by him at the retreat of Count of <hi>Horne,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged the Prince of <hi>Liege.</hi> See there, theſe be the good &amp; charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Offices, which this diſsembling Patriot intends to practice for the good of the Countryes. The letter which he ſent to the States, was almoſt of the ſame tenure and contents as that written to her Highneſse: we will onely examine theſe things which are of note and moment. He ſaith that he had given advice <hi>that the place of the enemies meeting or rendevons ſhould be at</hi> Moock <hi>neereſt of all to his Government.</hi> He would ſpeake according to knowledge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the place, and not without reaſon, but hee might know ſince it was he that had called the enemy thither. But is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe that hee gave them any advertizement or notice at all, but onely at the very inſtant when the enemy arrived.</p>
            <p>He propoſeth <hi>his naturall affection vnto the good of the Countries.</hi> He is a ſtranger, revengefull, full of ill will and malice, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends and labours to make a private diſcontent &amp; grudge a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cauſe, he ſtomacks the Marquiſe <hi>De Leganes,</hi> who hath beene indeed rayſed in theſe Countries to be a Patriot, him he accuſeth imprudently, and unadviſedly of ſuch buſineſse which he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acquainted withall, the ſaid Marquiſe at that time not being intereſsed in the matter. If hee thinke himſelfe wronged in any thing, it is lawfull for him to right himſelfe by an ordinary courſe,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176890:8"/>But not to commit ſuch a looſeneſse, and to play the little Tyrant. What have theſe Countries to doe with his particular quarels &amp; heart-burning? If his courage had had edges ſharpe enough, and wings ſwift enough for honour, and that he thought himſelfe ſo grievouſly offended, as he ſpeakes of: as oftentimes as hee hath had occaſion to ſee the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quiſe Nay more, as often as hee hath ſeene him, who hath hindered him from demanding him ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? <hi>As for the Spaniſh Nation which he complaines doe wiſh his death, and that they ſhot at his Picture, which hangs neere the Steen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> he hath exceeding great wrong, for if it be true, that the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> be ſuch as hee ſpeaketh of, they had all of them long ſince beene made away, and he who for the preſent ſerves for Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, hath oftentimes inculcated the meanes to deſtroy them, and ſaid that therein hee went in the Kings ſervice; But his Oracles ſounded alwayes ſo little profitable to the King, that no truſt might be given to his perſwaſions: It hath proved better, to goe a milder way to worke, and to ſtrive to redreſſe whatſoever was amiſſe by gifts, and employments, than to practiſe any ſuch extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, which the world would never have judged worthy to bee executed, if the proofe had not beene drawne, as now it is by his owne declaration.</p>
            <p>It is very pretty that he complaines of the <hi>Spaniſh, becauſe they ſhot at his Picture:</hi> his ſpyes would have much a doe to bring ſufficient witneſſe for the proofe thereof, although (to be true &amp; plaine) he that betrayes his Prince deſerves othergeſſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than he that onely exerciſeth his treaſon againſt his picture. It was he, the felon, who ſo lately on the 27. of <hi>Iune</hi> was ſo raſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and impudent as might lye in the City of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> by the patrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious hands of his wicked adhaerents cauſed attempt to bee made againſt the ſacred Image of the King his Lord and good Maſter, by that meanes to endeavour to begin by that execrable fact the firſt exployts of his rebellion. But the contrary of which they inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded is happened, and the wicked projects of theſe imps prevayled not, for two dayes after the States of <hi>Braband</hi> not being able any longer to endure the indignity of this abomination, of their owne proper motion, came perſonally in publike audience, to the great edification of all that were preſent, and preſented themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176890:9"/>the Princeſſe, and there renewed ſolemnely the Oath of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and allegeance to the King their Prince, and Naturall Lord, &amp; to her Highneſſe, declaring that they were ready to take the ſame Oath to the Prince of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for thoſe <hi>Offices and charges</hi> which he ſayes, <hi>are not conferred upon any bat Spaniards.</hi> I muſt here needs repeat, that hee himſelfe at their concluſion, had the principall of all, but hee hath very ill diſcharged himſelfe, and I muſt ſay that his ingratitude hath ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bounds nor limits. Wicked ſervant as he is, he never ſerved but by intereſt, and never Prince was more liberall to any man, than our Princeſſe haue beene to him. Never did hee march forth with the Armies but in the upſhot he obtayned ſome ſummes of moneys for his particular, and ever received more than any <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> or Lord of the Countrey, beſides thoſe ſecret gratuities and benefites which hee obtayned under hand, whereof hee never made any account but applyed them to his private gaine &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. He knowes well enough how punctually he cauſed all reareges to be payd him downe before ever he would ſet one foote on the way to the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> In a word for that eſtate &amp; ſubſtance which now he hath, he is more obliged than any man in the world for it, and to that King againſt whom hee now takes up Armes.</p>
            <p>From a meane Soldier hee was made a Captaine of Horſe, afterward Maſter of the Campe, hee was truſted with the City of <hi>Oldenzel;</hi> afterward with <hi>Groll,</hi> and at laſt hee had the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Province of <hi>Geldres,</hi> which than was one of the beſt and faireſt Province of all the Countries, hee hath alſo had the generall Government of the Cavallery, and the Generalſhip of the Artillery, he hath commanded the whole Army, and alwayes with retention of the wages of all places and charge which formerly he exerciſed; to be ſhort, In the yeare 1629. he was by her Highneſſe in the name of the King made Generall Maſter of the Campe of the whole Army of his Majeſty. Whereunto could his ambition aſpire higher unleſſe it were to Tyrannie which he now affects at this preſent? Our enemies themſelves with whom he hath held correſpondency and wrought his miſchievous practiſes a long time have beene aſtoniſhed many times, that ſo many recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould prodigally bee laviſhed and waſted upon one who was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176890:9"/>ſo vndeſeruing and demeriting. Laſt of all, which is more, when the Earle of <hi>Stryrum</hi> entred into <hi>Gueldres</hi> with the Enemies troupes, ſeeing the County of <hi>Montfort,</hi> which is worth more in reueneus than twentie thouſand Florins, and which the King had given to Count <hi>Henry de Bergh,</hi> with many other Townes and villages of the Country of <hi>Stefens wert,</hi> hee could not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold nor abſtaine from ſaying, that hee marvailed much how the King could find in his heart to beſtow ſo much vpon one of a contrary party. Adding withall, that if he ſhould haue ſerued the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> an hundred yeares, hee would not haue beene requited with ſuch an honourable reward.</p>
            <p>As for his Expreſſion. <hi>That he invites vs to accept of one of his paſſions, and to take another courſe vnder the gouernment of her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> Wee thanke him for his good will, and to thanke God that hee hath beene pleaſed to diſcover vnto vs and Enemie, who could ſo cloſely and covertly hatch and plot our ruine and deſtruction, if he had but ſo much ayde and conduct, as hee is full of euill moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and intentions. Our wiſe Princeſſe hath no need of ſuch a Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to diſſipate and ſcatter abroad the Patrimony of the King her Nephew. And deſolate and ruinate a Country ſo well gouerned, which for many yeares together hath coſt his Maieſtie all the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hes of <hi>Spaine</hi> and the <hi>Indyes,</hi> and the blood of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſpilt for the ſafety and preſervation of the ſame and for the Catholick Faith and Religion.</p>
            <p>There remaines yet his Declaration, which is nothing elſe but a manifeſtation of his diſcontent, and a profer of entertainment vnto thoſe that will bee his followers.</p>
            <p>It is very well knowne that he bath moneyes and good ſtore of Coine, if hee had no more but what hee hath gotten by the Paſſeports which hee continually ſold without ceaſing, whileſt the licencyes were ſhut, and the traffick and commerce, prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and interdicted with the rebellious Provinces. It is alſo well known that he hath receiued many gifts &amp; preſents from Princes and thoſe people that were neare adioyning neighbours vnto his Government. No, theſe things wee are no more ignorant of, than wee are of the monies which hee ſtill hath in his hands, for which pence of ſiluer hee treacherouſly ſold his Maiſter; but his inſatiable couetouſneſſe would neuer ſuffer him to vſe his riches
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176890:10"/>liberally towards thoſe which were honeſt and good men. There is not one ſoldier that knowes him, who doth not alſo know the ſmall account which he makes of them, and who doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how euilly he hath alwaies intreated them in his gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, cutting off from them the commodities, which in other places the Country people did not deny them, to extort moſt exo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bitant contributions for his owne particular; ſo that certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you may beleeue (my Lords) that the ſoldiers will giue no more credency to his declaration than your honours haue done to his letters.</p>
            <p>You haue witneſſed the condemnation which you haue made, your good zeale toward Religion, your ſincere affection to the Princeſſe, and your duties in the behalfe of the Countryes. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſhall euer bee obliged vnto you, the King ſhall euer acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your loyaltye and accept of your fidelity, the Princeſſe doth highly eſteeme and commend, yea reioyce in your affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, ſhee embraceth them, and gives you hearty thankes. And the Countryes ſhall ſee their owne preſervation by your meane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Doe ſo much more for the publick good, that hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward all thoſe that audaciouſly and preſumptuouſly ſhall dare to take part and adioyne themſelues to this new Tyrant, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect his cauſe ſo vniuſt and deteſtable, may bee reputed and accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as fauourers, and complotters of his Rebellion.</p>
            <p>As for the reſt that concernes the plots practices and diuiſes of our Enemies remember the coſt and charges of the time paſt, that all the Inventions of liberty of conſcience which now he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, haue not beene invented for any other end but meerely to ruine the beautifull foundation of our Religion, to eſtabliſh an hundred other new ones, and to corrupt the tenderneſſe of our Children by the pernicious examples, and introduction of hereſie. Theſe are the wayes &amp; cunning windings which our enemies goe and walke in. Theſe are the enchanted kindneſses which they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto us. Should we have a heart to receive ſuch impoyſoned gifts, which are profered us by the hand of an enemy? Who ſhould then furniſh and provide us with Prelates and Prieſts, and perſons neceſſary for our Ceremonies, for the comfort and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of our Soules, the eaſe and peace of our Conſciences? When
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176890:10"/>our Prelates ſhall be deceaſed, whence ſhould wee have new ones bred amongſt us? What Apoſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icall Bulles would authorize them? Who would ſet them in poſſeſſion, when our enemies hold this for a maxime and foundation, not to acknowledge the Romiſh Church. And laſt of all what aſsured treaty and contract could we make with our victorious enemies, and their cautions which at this day doe trouble whole <hi>Europe,</hi> and leave not one corner of the World where the Catholickes are not perſecuted ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by effect, or apprehenſion in the expectation of the progreſse of Armes, and by the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our of the Heretique.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
